上溯至宇宙初始 周遭还只是一片漆黑
In the beginning, there was darkness.
不知何时 忽地一声巨响
And then... Bang!
时间空间以及物质皆由此发端
Giving birth to an endless expanding existence
此后不断膨胀 延伸 永无止境
of time, space, and matter.
每一天 新的发现都在不断为我们解开
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking
蕴藏于这里的那些神秘莫测
the mysterious, the mind-blowing,
令人大开眼界 致命的秘密
the deadly secrets of a place we call
我们称这个地方为"宇宙"
the universe.
彗星以一往无前的气概
Chart a daring course with comets,
在宇宙里进行着漫长的旅行
the cosmic time travelers of the skies.
这些神秘物体曾被视为异兆
These mysteious objects have been agents of change.
它们曾被认为是灾星
They've been agents of destruction.
这些天体携带着以前的秘密
Discover why these celestial bodies
如果了解其中原因
carry secrets from our past
就可以让我们把握未来
and cast doom over our future.
如果它冲着我们而来
If it's getting into our on-ramp,
我们就得担心吊胆
we need to worry about it.
除了发射巨型原子弹
There's very little we can do
让它们偏离方向
other than sending a giant bomb toward them
我们别无选择
and trying to deflect them.
让我们迎上这些冰冷的
Brace yourself as we rendezvous
来自宇宙深处的不速之客
with the frozen intruders from the great beyond
展开壮丽的"与彗星同行"之旅
on an epic journey to "Ride the Comet."
宇宙:与彗星同行
它们悄然出现
They appear out of nowhere,
缓缓地划过漆黑夜空
gliding slowly across the nighttime sky
然后消失在视线之外
and then disappearing from sight.
许多古文明认为
Throughout human history, ancient cultures
这些不速之客
believed these celestial intruders
拥有上帝赋予的特殊力量
carried special powers from the gods,
蕴藏着生与死的神秘信息
mystical messengers of life and death.
科学家认为
Scientists like to think
彗星相当神秘
that comets are fairly mysterious objects,
这是因为它们非常古老
because we know that they're very old.
好象是来自太阳系诞生时期
They're like frozen time capsules
把时间冻结起来的密封舱
from when our solar system was first formed.
彗星耀眼夺目
Comets are a bit of show-offs.
在夜空里 来无影 去无踪
They come into the night sky unannounced, unpredicted.
它们在中世纪被认为是
In the Middle Ages, they were thought to be fireballs
怒火中烧的上帝
thrown at a sinful Earth
掷向罪恶地球的火球
from the right hand of an avenging god.
被视为畏惧之物 或是诡秘的东西
And so they've always been feared or seen as mysterious.
让我们勇敢地
We're going to hitch a ride
踏上茫茫旅程 去了解太阳系里
on a bold, uncharted journey through the secret life
彗星的秘密生活
of our solar system's comets.
我们坐着时光穿梭机
Our daring quest begins 4.5 billion years ago,
从45亿年前太阳系诞生的时候
as our futuristic spacecraft time-travels
开始我们的无畏之旅
back to the birth of our solar system.
我们曲折地穿过碎石群
We zigzag through a maelstrom of debris
去开始研究
to catch our first glimpse of comets,
这些自由任性 不肯与行星结合的石头堆
the wayward rocks that didn't meld into planets.
彗星其实是肮脏的雪球
Comets are basically dirty snowballs
或者结冰的脏球
or icy dirtballs.
它们是由岩石 灰尘和脏东西
They consist of rocks and dust and dirt
在冰块的作用下混合而成
held together by ices-
冰块里包含有水 氨 甲烷和二氧化碳干冰
water ice, ammonia, methane, carbon dioxide, dry ice.
它就象是胶水
That's sort of like the glue
把小石头和尘埃
that holds all these little pebbles
牢牢地粘在一起
and particles of dust together.
这些冰团最主要的部分是彗核
The heart of these cosmic icebergs is the nucleus,
彗核也叫中央核心 它们的直径
or central core, which averages in size
有的长半英里 有的象一个现代城市这么大
from a half mile wide to as big as a modern city.
通过近距离观察
One of the things we've learned
我们发现彗核
by flying close by and observing the nuclei of comets
它们是奇怪的
is that they're these strange
冰和岩石的聚合物
sort of compacted conglomerates of ice and rock.
彼此不相同
They're not uniform.
它们不是紧密的聚合体
They're not perfectly mixed.
非常粗短 形状古怪
They're quite chunky and oddly shaped.
彗核
The nuclei of comets are...
非常易碎
very fragile entities.
如果手里有一块
If you had a chunk,
你能轻而易举地折断它
you could probably break it easily in your hands.
准确来讲 与其说彗星象超大号雪球
Up close, comets look like bland chunks of charcoal
不如说它象大木炭
rather than supersized snowballs.
它们与我们在漆黑天空里
They don't even remotely resemble
见到的发光圆形天体
the glowing orbs we see
相去甚远
in our pitch-black skies.
我们认为绝大多数彗星
We think that most comets are extremely dark
其表面非常黑 覆盖着
on their surfaces, that the surfaces are covered
类似于烧烤烟灰的东西
with something kind of like barbecue soot,
这种物质黑色无光
this really dark, black material
让彗星非常难被观察到
that makes them very difficult to see.
由于它们的远亲小行星
While their asteroid cousins
也拥有类似的物质 比如岩石和金属
share similar properties, such as rock and metal,
科学家们怀疑彗星产生于更遥远的
scientists suspect that comets were born farther out,
毗邻着气态巨行星的地方
near the gas giant planets,
那里寒冷至极
where it's much colder,
所以它们有很多的冰和易挥发成分
so they possess more ices and volatile elements.
大约38亿年前 在寒冷的柯伊伯带
About 3.8 billion years ago, many of these icy bodies
这个与太阳系最外侧的海王星相毗邻的区域里
were whisked away to the Kuiper belt, a frigid neighborhood
许多冰团被甩了出来
just beyond the outermost planet, Neptune.
柯伊伯带里的冰团或许会飞向太阳
Icy objects in the Kuiper belt probably formed
但那里有许多巨型行星
closer in toward the Sun, where the giant planets are,
巨型行星们联手施加万有引力
but then gravitational interactions with those giant planets
从而让它们逃出了太阳的魔爪
made those icy objects migrate outward.
我们飞船所穿越的
Our spacecraft navigates
这一片黑暗的圆盘状区域
through this dark, disklike region,
大约20亿英里宽
which is almost 2 billion miles wide
估计里面的彗星超过60亿颗
and is estimated to hold over 6 billion comets.
我们最后降落在其中一块冰团的表面
We eventually touch down on the surface of one of these icy boulders.
登陆彗星相当棘手
Landing on a comet would be a pretty tricky affair.
在肮脏的冰雪下面
So you could kind of imagine dirty snow
是气体
that's covered with exhaust,
如果在上面行走
and if you step on it, in places,
许多地方的表层不堪负荷
you can punch through to places where there's more
就会被穿透
fresh material underneath it.
柯伊伯带里的物体
The Kuiper belt objects
其轨道相当稳定
appear to have fairly stable orbits,
用来做顺风车没有太多意思
so they won't be that much fun to ride.
所以我们再次起飞
We lift off in search of a comet
去寻找穿越太阳系的彗星
that will cut a more exciting path
共赴激情之旅
through our solar system.
我们飞向更遥远的
We navigate farther out
行星稀少的"离散盘"
to a sparsely populated region called the scattered disc,
那里是冰团的家园 其轨道椭而长
which is home to icy bodies with long, elliptical orbits.
最细微的扰动也能让这些不稳定的物体
The slightest disturbance can send these unstable objects
猛冲进内太阳系
careening into the inner solar system,
成为我们所说的每20年至200年
where they become known as short-period comets,
环绕太阳一次的"短周期彗星"
those which orbit the Sun every 20 to 200 years.
那里行星稀少
The scattered disc region
被认为是短周期彗星的
is thought to be the primary source
主要发源地
of the short-period comets.
它们之所以被踢进内太阳系
They are kicked into the inner solar system
是因为海王星或路过的天体
either by interacting with Neptune
对它们施加影响的缘故
or possibly passing stars.
飞船里的我们
Our spacecraft witnesses
亲眼目睹了海王星的万有引力
Neptune's gravitational influence at work,
把一颗彗星甩出了离散盘
dislodging a comet out of the scattered disc.
登陆眼前的彗星 实在是太危险
This comet would be too dangerous to land on,
我们只能紧跟其后
so we'll track alongside it
去一睹其穿越太阳系的新生之旅
on its transformational flight through our solar system.
如果它飞向太阳 会发生什么情况？
So what would happen if it was on a journey toward the Sun?
一开始 它象黑色的行星
Well, it would start off looking like a dark asteroid.
什么都没有发生
Nothing much is happening.
它的周围没有大气
It doesn't have an atmosphere around it.
一到了内太阳系
As you start to travel toward the inner solar system,
接近木星 或是离太阳更近的时候
get up to Jupiter or even closer to the Sun,
彗星会开始变得活跃
the comet would start to become active.
太阳的温暖让彗星开始变热
The warmth from the Sun starts to heat up the comet,
其内部的冰冻物质
and all the frozen material that's trapped on the inside
开始从冰转化为气态
starts to convert from ice into gaseous material,
穿透彗星的外层
and so these gas jets can actually punch through
形成喷射气流
the crust of the comet and form jets.
喷射气流离开表面时
As these jets flow away from the surface,
会把尘埃和石头一起冲出
they can start to pull dust and rocks with them,
形成了笼罩彗核的烟雾
and this forms a kind of hazy atmosphere around the comet's nucleus.
我们称之为"彗发"
We call this the coma.
从地球上观测
As it zooms by Earth,
彗发会渐渐变得
the coma of a comet can grow to be larger
比太阳的直径还要大
than the diameter of our Sun.
最后 太阳辐射把光环加在彗核后面
Solar radiation eventually pushes this cosmic halo
形成两条明亮的尾巴
behind the nucleus, forming two bright tails:
一条尘埃的 一条气体的
one of dust and the other of gas.
尾巴将会越长越大
There will be a tail growing and growing and growing,
而紧随其后的你
and you would eventually become engulfed
被包裹在夹杂尘埃的石头和冰块当中
in just a really rocky, icy, particle-filled environment.
你的飞船将难以飞行
It would be very difficult on your spacecraft
就好象是在暴风雪中穿梭
because it'd be like flying through a blizzard.
有些尾巴会延伸至1亿英里长
Some tails can stretch for 100 million miles,
这意味着 在朝太阳进发的时候
more than the distance between the Sun and the Earth,
彗尾比太阳和地球的间距还要长
as it travels towards our home star.
这是太阳系里最壮丽的奇观之一
It's one of the most spectacular spectacles of our solar system.
现在 我们一起看看
Today we're going to see what happens
如果让位于寒冷 漆黑的太阳系外围
when we take a comet that's been in the cold, dark, icy outer reaches
被冰封的彗星
of the solar system,
向着近日点 即是最接近太阳的点逼近
and we're going to send it inward towards its perihelion,
会发生什么情况
or the point of closest approach to the Sun.
干冰是冰冻的二氧化碳
Now, dry ice is frozen carbon dioxide,
它是彗星非常普遍的成份
and this is a very common constituent of comets.
请注意了
Let's see what happens.
我们把干冰
When we take this piece of dry ice,
放进温暖的水中
and we drop it into the warm water,
它开始升华
the dry ice starts to sublimate.
这说明它直接从冻结的固态
That means it converts directly from a solid, frozen state
转变为气态
into a gaseous state.
而由于干冰的某些部分
And as the water starts to warm up
首先被水加热
certain parts of the dry ice first,
所以开始出现微小的喷射流
you can start to see that little jets kind of form on it,
形成了被称为"彗发"的雾气
and this forms a hazy atmosphere called a coma.
在升华的过程中
You can see that the little chips of dry ice
干冰小碎片不停地变化着
are constantly changing as they sublimate away.
时而加速
Sometimes they speed up.
时而慢下来
Sometimes they slow down.
所以 如果它是彗星
So if this was a comet,
你能想象得到 当彗星接近太阳
you can get the idea that, as the comet approaches the Sun,
不稳定的物质会开始蒸发
and the volatiles start to vaporize,
彗星的运行状态会发生改变
this can actually change the comet's rotational state
甚至轨道也会改变
and even its orbit.
在最靠近太阳的时候
Comets are brightest and fastest
彗星最明亮 最快
when they're closest to the Sun.
太阳的灼热和巨大的万有引力
The searing heat and immense gravity of our mother star
可以让彗星加速至
can accelerate a comet's speed
每小时将近2百万英里
to nearly 2 million miles per hour.
太阳使它的速度大幅增加
The speed increases a lot, and it whips around the Sun,
而且越来越快
so it goes zoom, like that,
如同一辆冲向低处的巨型过山车
like being propelled at the bottom of a giant roller coaster.
过山车刚从高处下落时 非常慢
A roller coaster starts out high, very slowly,
重力作用使它速度加快
picks up speed due to the gravity,
风驰电掣地通过低处
goes zooming past the bottom,
然后又再次慢下来
and then slows down again on its outward journey.
彗星最终会离太阳而去
Eventually, as our comet leaves the vicinity of the Sun,
返回到遥远的太阳系深处 继续不变的旅程
it's going to travel back out into the far reaches of the solar system.
一切会平息下来
Everything's going to quiet down.
所有的气体和尘埃将重新沉积回表面
All of the gas and dust is going to settle back onto its surface.
最后 整个彗星将没入宁静的黑暗中
And eventually, it'll cruise away into the quiet dark.
彗星回到寒冷的离散盘
Back in the cold region of the scattered disc,
再次变成
a comet transforms
晦暗无光的石头和冰
back into a dull, black lump of rock and ice
直到它再次去环绕太阳
until it makes its journey around the Sun once again.
哈雷是最著名的短周期彗星
Haley, the most famous short-period comet,
每76年经过地球一次
was first recorded in 240.C.
在公元前240年被首次记录下来
and has passed by Earth every 76 years.
家喻户晓的它
Estimated to be the size of Manhattan,
估计有曼哈顿那么大 非常明亮
this superstar comet is sometimes so bright,
在大白天也能看到
it has been seen in broad daylight.
在历史上
Throughout history,
哈雷的出现都会引起
the appearance of Haley has inspired awe and dread
地球人的敬畏和恐惧
among earthly observers.
在1910年 人们为此惊恐万分
In 1910, it was feared,
刚创立不久的光谱学
because spectroscopy had just been introduced,
让人们认为 彗星含有氰
and they had determined that comets contain cyanogen,
氰是一种无臭的有毒气体
which is an odorless and poisonous gas,
所以天文学家预测 这种毒气
and so astronomers predicted that there'd be problems
扫过地球时会带来麻烦
because of this poisonous gas sweeping the Earth,
给人类造成浩劫
and so there were actually comet pills manufactured.
当时的保险就删除了有关彗星的内容
Life insurance policies on the comet were taken out.
在彗星被认为是
While comets have been thought to be
天外死亡预言的同时
extraterrestrial harbingers of doom,
天文学家思考着 是否这些发光的石头
astronomers have long wondered if these glowing rocks
蕴藏着关于我们过去的珍贵信息
contain precious information about our past.
在21世纪 美国航天局 (NASA) 筹划了
By the 21st century, NASA was ready to ignite
一次异常大胆的撞击
a bold offensive strike,
希望可以对
one that would hopefully expose
被誉为行星科学终极目标之一的彗星进行揭秘
one of the holy grails of planetary science.
这些星际流浪者
Could these interplanetary vagabonds
曾经是宇宙生命的传递者吗？
have been the cosmic transporters of life?
迄今为止 我们与彗星一起
So far, we've traveled with comets
从寒冷 偏远的柯伊伯带和离散盘出发
from the frozen hinterlands of the Kuiper belt and scattered disc
飞赴激情的环绕太阳之旅
to an exhilarating orbit around the Sun.
在它形成明亮的彗发和彗尾的时候
We've watched these dark bodies come alive
我们看到了彗星爆发的活力
as they formed brilliant comas and tails.
但科学家们仍然
But scientists are still puzzled
对彗星内部有什么东西 感到困惑
about what's really inside these cosmic interlopers.
我希望了解彗星内部
Man, I wish I knew what the interior of a comet looked like.
很想看到彗核里的东西
You would love to be able to look inside the nucleus of a comet,
看看是不是块状 是不是千篇一律
to see if it's clumpy, if it's uniform.
有结晶的冰吗？
Is there crystalline ice?
有玻璃状的冰吗？
Is there glassy ice?
我们的神奇飞船
Our protective spacecraft
穿越时空 回到2005年
time-travels back to 2005
与NASA执行撞击彗星任务的
and meets up with NASA's Deep Impact space probe
"深度撞击号"相会
on a comet-hunting mission.
它撞击的目标
It zeroes in on a short-period comet named Tempel 1
是坦普尔1号短周期彗星
with an aggressive plan of attack.
深度撞击号向擦肩而过的彗星
We hover at a safe distance as Deep Impact
发射了一个800磅重的撞击器
launches an 800-pound projectile into the passing comet.
撞击器轰出一个弹坑
Debris sprays out for thousands of miles
碎片飞溅数千英里高
as the impactor excavates a crater
数以吨计的气体 岩石和尘埃被抛入太空
and sends tons of blinding gas, rocks, and dust into space.
在人类历史上
or the first time in history,
这或许是科学家首次能够
scientists are able to peer inside
仔细观察彗星内部的冰封世界
the icy, muddy interior of a comet.
在撞击后
Right after the impact,
硅酸盐颗粒强烈反光 极为明亮
you could see silicate grains fluorescing and glowing.
这就说明 彗星是非常原始
This tells us that comets are very primitive material
它们让物质基本保持了
and that they pretty much do preserve in pristine state
恒星形成最初期的原始状态
the materials that we find in the youngest star-forming systems.
所以 它们是时间的密封舱
So indeed, they really are time capsules
能让我们追溯到
that let us look back on our own solar system
太阳系的最早期
at the very beginning.
在深度撞击号
While Deep Impact
对彗星内部一窥究竟的时候
captures a rare glimpse of a comet's interior,
由于碎片太多太细 景象模糊不清
it is unable to snap clear images of the crater,
它未能得到清晰的弹坑照片
which was obscured by an enormous plume of debris.
在2011年2月
In February 2011,
另一艘宇宙飞船"星尘-延续任务号"
another spacecraft, named Stardust-NExT,
追赶上五年绕太阳一次的
catches up to Tempel 1
坦普尔1号彗星
as it completes its five-year orbit around the Sun.
让每个人都吃惊的是
To everyone's surprise,
五年前历史性的撞击
the impact crater is much smaller than had been expected
所留下的弹坑比预料的小得多
from the historic smash-up that occurred five years earlier.
真奇怪
Amazing...
弹坑看起来比较小
But the crater looked like it was small.
由此引发了一个争议
So this now creates this issue:
弹坑总是这么小吗？
Was the crater always small?
弹坑与我们预想的不同
We know the crater isn't what we expected.
所以要进行一些实验
So we're going to do some experiments
看看能否解释个中原因
to see if we can explain why the crater looks like it does.
太阳灯来了
Sunlamp's coming on.
可以上移一点吗？
Can we move it up a bit?
在NASA的艾姆斯垂直射击靶场
At NASA's Ames Vertical Gun Range,
"星尘-延续任务"的负责人皮特.舒尔茨
Stardust-NExT coinvestigator Pete Schultz
正在安排高速撞击试验 以便弄明白
is conducting high-velocity impact experiments
深度撞击号留下的弹坑怎么那么小
to find out why Deep Impact produced such a tiny crater.
他将会用一支巨大的点30口径高速气枪
He will use a massive .30-caliber high-velocity gas gun
发射细小的子弹
to fire tiny projectile beads at various targets
打向真空室里的目标
located inside a vacuum chamber.
我们正试图模拟
We're trying to simulate
9P/Tempel 1 彗星的真实表面
what the nature of the surface of comet 9P/Tempel 1 is like,
所以我们放入珍珠岩
so we're putting in perlite,
这种低密度的园林材料
which is this low-density material that you find in gardens,
再加入中空的小球粒
then we're adding in hollow microspheres,
让它更加类似于真实的彗星表面
and this also resemble what the nature of the comet is like.
实验的目的是
The purpose of the experiment is to see what happens
观察弹坑的形成
to the crater after formation.
会有弹坑吗？它会坍塌吗？
Does it stay there? Does it collapse?
实验之后 将真相大白
With this experiment, we should be able to find out.
好了 我走出箱子了
Okay, I'm out of the tank.
准备开始
Lock and load.
高速摄影机遍布真空室四周
High-speed cameras mounted around the vacuum chamber
将对撞击进行记录
will document the impact.
我们象离弦的箭
We've got this one covered.
只能命中目标
We just have to hit the target.
好了
Okay.
让我们动手吧
Let's shoot this puppy.
J.P. 好了吗？
J.P., are you ready?
好了
Yeah.
焦急等待的时候
As the crew anxiously awaits in the control room,
皮特做出了一个迷信的举动
Pete mixes science with a little superstition.
风险始终存在
There's always a risk.
有时会失败 有时会成功
Sometimes you miss. Sometimes you hit.
噢 天哪
Oh, sweet.
它塌了下来
The whole thing sort of collapses in on itself.
变小了
It's getting smaller now.
开始大 现在小
It was bigger. Now it's getting smaller.
许多尘埃和喷射物飞溅起来
So what we see here is that there's a lot of dust and ejecta
填充了弹坑
sent upwards, and that blocked the view.
弹坑不成样子
We couldn't see the crater forming.
因此 美丽的弹坑在眨眼间
So what started off being a nice-looking crater,
不见了
it just doesn't stay there.
它自我恢复了
It just simply heals itself.
所以 9P/Tempel 1彗星可能也是如此
So what may have happened for 9P/Tempel 1,
对弹坑进行了自我恢复
the nucleus, is that that crater healed itself.
也就是说 彗核自我治愈了
The nucleus healed itself from the scar created
深度撞击号带来的创伤
by us with Deep Impact.
让我们去看看
Let's see what we did.
这个结果很奇怪
So the results were fantastic.
我们检查了原来的计划
We got to see just what we planned to.
发现不是这么简单
There may be more to the story,
所以还要做另一个不同的实验
so we're going to try a different experiment as well.
皮特有一个预感
Pete has a hunch
深度撞击任务有疏漏之处
there's a missing piece to the Deep Impact mission.
他现在想知道 航天探测器
He now wants to see if the space probe
是否因为坦普尔1号核心的构造
created a different type of crater on Tempel 1,
而产生一个不同类型的弹坑
due to the makeup of the comet's nucleus.
眼下 我们将在
So this time, we're going to put
珍珠岩下面放一层密度大的东西
a denser layer below that perlite,
去确认一下
so we want to find out whether or not
能否得到一个不同类型的弹坑
we'll get a different type of crater
如果我们使用上软下密
if we have two different types of material:
这两种不同类型的材料的话
one very soft on top and one denser on the bottom.
皮特和队员回到控制室观察
Pete and his crew return to the control room
底下铺着厚厚一层沙子的珍珠岩
to see what happens to the new target of perlite
这个新靶子
poured over a heavier layer of sand.
这次在珍珠岩上形成了一个大弹坑
Now, that formed a big crater in the perlite.
请仔细看
Boy, look at that.
噢 哥们 太棒了
Oh, oh, man, that is gorgeous.
好
Okay.
子弹钻进深处
The projectile went deep,
击起了无数的碎片
and now the stuff is coming back out that hole,
向洞外四处飞溅
while, on the surface, it's excavating debris.
砰 好
Pow! Okay.
双层靶子产生的不是一个
The double-layered target created not one
而是两个弹坑
but two craters,
小的弹坑是在大而浅的弹坑内部
a small crater inside a larger, shallower crater.
在9P/Tempel 1彗星上也会如此
This could be what happened for 9P/Tempel 1.
射弹钻进彗核很深的地方
It went so deep into the nucleus,
然后引起坍塌
and then it just simply collapses away,
我们在外面只能看到非常不起眼的圆环
and we're left with just this very, very faint rim
其中心也只是一个小凹点
on the outside with a small pit in the center.
这些撞击实验
These impact experiments
为研究坦普尔1号彗星提供了意外的线索
yield surprising clues about the interior of Tempel 1
甚至可能适用于所有的彗星
and perhaps all comets.
彗星历史悠久
Now we know that comets have history.
由不同的层组成
We see layers.
但我不清楚彗核
I don't know if these layers go all the way
是通体如一
through the nucleus,
还是各层相互不同？
or are they only in one part?
解开彗星内部之迷
Unraveling the secrets
将有助于科学家去了解
of what's inside comets will help scientists understand
是什么使得它们行为怪异
what causes them to exhibit some really bizarre behavior.
去与哈特利2号见面
as it encounters Hartley 2,
那是一颗快速旋转的彗星
a fast-spinning comet that tumbles through space
好象一颗在太空里不停翻转的花生
like a hyperactive cosmic peanut.
哈特利2号比较小
Hartley 2 is a smaller comet.
直径只有大约一英里
It's only about a mile or so across,
因此它异常活跃
and so it's kind of a surprise that it's so active.
它喷射出大量的二氧化碳和氰气流
It's putting off huge amounts of CO2 and, actually, cyanide gas.
但问题是 是所有小彗星都如此活跃
And the question is, are all small comets active like this
还是少数？
or only a few?
还有 是什么让它们如此活跃？
And what makes them so active?
这里有一个小塑料瓶
I've got a peanut-shaped plastic bottle here
假设它是哈特利2号
that's supposed to represent comet Hartley 2.
它里面装满了干冰和热水
It's full of dry ice and warm water,
可以看到
and as you can see,
热水开始让干冰升华
as the warm water starts to make the dry ice sublimate,
并从瓶子上的洞
it shoots out these jets
喷射出气流
through the holes that we've got poked in the bottle.
如果我把它放到水里
If I drop it into the water,
不再用手拿着
instead of holding it fixed in space,
喷射气流会立即让瓶子
you can see that the jets actually start
发生旋转
pushing the bottle around,
这就是彗星运行状态改变的原因
causing the comet's rotational state to change.
它非常类似于哈特利2号的情形
This is very similar to what's going on on the surface of comet Hartley 2.
二氧化碳喷射流改变了彗星的运行
The CO2 jets are actually changing the rotational state
导致它时快时慢
of the comet, causing it to speed up and slow down.
跟踪哈特利2号的时候
When tracking Hartley 2,
我们的飞船遇上了宇宙里的暴风雪
our spacecraft gets caught in a cosmic blizzard
这颗彗星神经质地喷出冰冻的雪球
as the spastic comet burps and belches out
在宇宙间绵延数百万英里
a trail of frozen snowballs that extend for millions of miles.
哈特利2号带来的惊奇之一
One of the big surprises about Hartley 2
是环绕着它的一群微型彗星
is that it was surrounded by this posse of mini comets.
那是喷发出来的冰雪球
This is simply ices that are coming off,
尺寸甚至有篮球这样大
about the size of a snowball all the way up to a basketball.
科学家怀疑这些雪球大小的碎块
Scientists suspect the snowball-sized debris
下雨般回落到哈特利2号上
rains back down on Hartley 2,
形成弹坑和高峰无数的奇异景观
producing its unusual landscape of craters and towering spires.
这些彗星的引力非常小
Because these comets have very little gravities,
绝大多数气体被刮进了宇宙
most of the gas is blown out into space,
只有非常少的一部分再沉积回表面
but a very small fraction can actually redeposit
在那里形成非常平滑的结构
on the surface, generating very smooth textures,
而在其它的地方 或是坑洼不平
and on other locations, generating these very bumpy
或是高峰林立
or spire-like texture.
告别了哈特利2号
From Hartley 2,
我们向太阳系的最外沿进发
we blast off to the extreme outer edge of our solar system,
那里空旷阴森
a vast, eerie place,
太阳的万有引力鞭长莫及
barely within the gravitational grasp of our Sun
即使凭借现代化的望远镜 也难以看到
and impossible to see, even with modern telescopes.
我们在银河邻居这里
Here, we come upon the largest
已经邂逅了
and perhaps most elusive
最大的 可能是最不可捉摸的冰团
icy bodies in our galactic neighborhood.
迷人的彗星世界
Our journey through the fascinating world of comets
给我们的旅程增添了无限惊喜
has provided us a ringside seat to some of the greatest
让我们欣赏到了不少精彩的宇宙表演秀
cosmic shows observed from Earth and space.
我们现在改变航线
We now change course and travel
去跨越比地球到太阳还远5万倍的距离
over 50,000 times the distance between Earth and the Sun
奔向我们太阳系的最外沿
to the outermost edge of our solar system.
我们抵达了奥尔特云
We arrive at the Oort cloud,
一个非常大的彗星云集地
an even larger fraternity of comets,
其数量可能超过一万亿个
perhaps over a trillion of them.
如果我们的飞船
If we'd actually got in a spaceship
想游览整个奥尔特云
and tried to go out and, say, visit the Oort cloud,
那将会是一段漫长旅程
this would have been a long journey.
那里的物体不可计数
There's billions and billions of these objects,
彼此间相隔遥远
and there's a lot of space in between them.
与柯伊伯带和离散盘相似
Like the Kuiper belt and scattered disc,
奥尔特云物体和太阳的形成时间可能很接近
the Oort cloud objects may have formed closer to the Sun,
但在太阳系形成大约8亿年后
but about 800 million years after the solar system was formed,
气态巨行星的引力
the gravitational influence of the gas giant planets
把这些彗星
flung these comets
扔到了寒冷的太阳系外沿
out to the frigid edge of our solar system.
一些物体以非常椭的轨道 被往外扔到了
Some of these objects were flung into very highly elliptical orbits
奥尔特云
out into the Oort cloud.
路过的星体使它们的轨道变圆
Passing stars could circularize those orbits,
并让它们在一定程度上稳定下来
making somewhat stable orbits for them.
大多数奥尔特云物体
Most of the Oort cloud bodies
自从太阳系诞生之后
have been in frozen hibernation
一直处在寒冷的冬眠世界里
since the birth of our solar system.
只有在轨道受到影响的时候
They only become long-period comets
它们才会变成长周期彗星
when they get sucked into orbits
冲向太阳系内的行星和太阳
that carry them inward towards the planets and the Sun.
科学家们还没有得到过
Scientists have never actually captured
奥尔特云的影像
an image of the Oort cloud,
但他们很有理由相信它在那里
but they have good reason to believe it's there.
即使距离太远 看起来模糊不清
Even though scientists can't directly observe the Oort cloud
科学家不能直接研究奥尔特云
because it's so far away and so faint,
但他们能够推断它的存在
what they are able to do is infer its existence
因为我们能研究
because we can look at
那些从四面八方游弋而来的
where all these long-period comets come from on the sky,
长周期彗星
and they seem to come from all different directions.
它们到来的方向不太一样
There doesn't really seem to be a preferred direction for them.
这就说明奥尔特云很可能
This suggests that the Oort cloud,
大致是圆的 如果它存在的话
if it exists, is probably roughly spherical.
一个巨大的疑问是
One of the big mysteries
到底是什么东西横蛮地撞击这些冰团
is what knocks these icy bodies off course
让它们游弋到了地球附近
and sends them cruising by our neighborhood of Earth.
奥尔特云的彗星很容易受到太阳系外
The comets in the Oort cloud are very susceptible to gravitational pulls from other things
其它物体引力的影响
outside the solar system.
其中一种是路过的星体
One thing is passing stars.
如果一个星体碰巧靠近太阳
If a star happens to come close to our Sun,
它会把彗星从奥尔特云外围驱散
it can scatter comets from the outer Oort cloud.
在太阳系经过银河系某一颗行星时
Icy objects in the Oort cloud can also be dislodged
奥尔特云的冰团
by gravitational perturbations that occur
会因为受到引力而发生移动
when the solar system goes through the plane of our galaxy.
太阳系主要围绕银河系中心运转
So the solar system is basically orbiting around the center of our galaxy,
但它也会周期性地往上或往下
but it's also oscillating up and down,
当它经过某一颗行星时
and when it goes through the plane,
万有引力会扰动奥尔特云物体
then gravitational interactions can perturb objects
进入到内太阳系
from the Oort cloud into the inner solar system.
一些长周期彗星
Some long-period comets
需要花费大约三千万年
take up to about 30 million years
才能完成绕太阳一周
to complete one round trip around the Sun.
我们的飞船尾随着
Our spacecraft tracks a long-period comet
一颗长周期彗星长途跋涉
for hundreds of thousands of miles
来到了地球的附近
until we approach planet Earth.
随着它张开冰冷的尾巴
As its icy tails unfurl,
一阵尘埃和冰雪
a layer of dust and ice zips through
在地球稀薄的大气里尖啸
our planet's thin atmosphere,
人们把这种景象称为流星雨
Leaving visible trails known as a meteor shower.
我认为
I like to think of comets
彗星相当于太阳系的猪窝
as sort of the pigpens of the solar system,
在绕行太阳的时候
because, as they orbit around the Sun,
留下了大量凌乱的残渣
they leave a big, messy trail of debris.
当地球横穿过其中一些尘埃团
But sometimes the Earth's orbit can intersect some of these dust bands,
我们就能看到流星雨的出现
and when it does, we can sometimes see meteor showers.
这些划破夜空
Those beautiful bright streaks of light
美丽耀眼的光芒
that you see coming through the night sky
其实只是
are actually produced by particles
砂粒般大小的颗粒所产生的
that are most often no bigger than a sand grain.
随着不断研究
While longand short-period comets
各种长短周期彗星
make up the bulk of comets that have been observed,
有新证据表明 不是所有的冰团
new evidence suggests that not all icy bodies
都来自于太阳系里零下温度的地方
come from the subzero suburbs of our solar system.
有一些是偷偷地躲藏在
Some have secretly taken up residence
非常暖和的区域里
in a much warmer neighborhood.
科学家们现在已发现
Scientists have now discovered
在木星和火星之间的小行星带里
there are comets masquerading as asteroids
存在着伪装成小行星的彗星
in the asteroid belt, located between Jupiter and Mars.
主带彗星的产生只有一个原因
The only reason that we've discovered these main-belt comets
那就是在偶然间
is because, occasionally,
太阳温暖的射线进入彗星内核
the warming rays of the Sun get into the interior,
使冰块汽化
vaporize the ices,
彗星不一会就突然爆裂
and so the comet just bursts forth for a while,
然后它们重新成为不活跃的物体或者小行星
and then they go back to being inactive objects or asteroids.
科学家以前曾认为 行星和彗星
Scientists used to think that there were strong distinctions
有很大的差别
between asteroids and comets
它们是两种完全不同的物体
and that they were two totally different types of objects,
但现在人们发现
but what we're finding nowadays is,
一些行星具有象彗星一样的特性
there are some asteroids that have comet-like properties,
而有一些彗星
and there are some comets that eventually kind of look
极象小行星
like asteroids.
一些科学家认为主带彗星
Some scientists think main-belt comets
可能把水和孕育生命的物质
may have delivered water to early Earth
带到了早期的地球
and the materials to create life.
我们回到2004年的1月份
We blast back to January 2004
跟随NASA的"星尘号"飞船去执行
and follow NASA's Stardust spacecraft
一项史无前例的任务
on an unprecedented mission
到太空里收集未受污染的彗星尘埃
to collect pure comet dust in space.
就在火星的附近
Just beyond the planet Mars,
我们遇到了"野生2"彗星
we meet up with a comet named Wild 2.
在靠近它的彗发时
Upon approaching its enormous coma,
星尘号伸出一个网球拍状
Stardust flips open a paddle-shaped collector tray
由牢固的泡沫气凝胶制成的收集器
filled with a durable foam-like substance called aerogel.
比尘粒还小的彗星微粒
Cometary particles no bigger than specks of dust
以6倍于出膛子弹的速度飞进气凝胶里
fly into the aerogel at six times the speed of a rifle bullet.
此任务的特别之处 是要保护好微粒的完整
The mission's task is to preserve the precious particles
不能破坏或改变它们
without damaging or altering them.
如果想在地球上把这演示出来 可不是容易的事
But this is no easy feat, as we show here on Earth.
在我身边的是康诺特.布鲁尔中士
We're here at a firing range with Sergeant Connacht Brewer,
他以前是伞兵
a former army paratrooper,
他将使用小号铅弹
who is going to demonstrate for us what happens
去射击巨大的粘土模型
when this birdshot strikes a large block of modeling clay.
这非常类似于
This is an excellent analogy for what happened
彗星微粒撞击到
when cometary particles impacted the aerogel
星尘号上的气凝胶
on the Stardust spacecraft.
略有不同的是
Except there, the particles were moving
微粒移动的速度比这种小号铅弹快50倍
about 50 times faster than this birdshot.
准备好了吗？
Ready to give it a go?
准备好了
Yes, I am.
请戴好护目镜 戴上耳塞
Go ahead and put on your eye protection and your earplugs.
我们将使用
What we're using for this today
雷明登12号1100型猎枪
is a 12-gauge Model 1100 Remington shotgun
射击大约35码外的目标
at a distance of about 35 yards.
即是说 我装填12号子弹
Basically, I'm just gonna load a 12-gauge shot shell
到猎枪里
into the shotgun...
然后开枪
And we're hot.
粘土模型千疮百孔
It really did some damage to that clay.
想看看吗？
You want to go take a look?
求之不得
Yeah, we're clear.
好
All right.
哇 千疮百孔
Wow, look at the damage it did to the clay.
每一颗子弹都形成了一个洞
Each pellet created one of these holes.
我们把它切成几块 好吗？
So what do you say we cut this open and try to find some pieces?
－ 这主意不错　－ 好的
- Sounds good. - All right.
看 粘土里的弹迹
So you see, the trail here that's formed inside the clay
能让你找到小号铅弹
is going to lead you, ultimately, to where the birdshot pellets are located.
通过眼前的实验 你能想象到
You can imagine how difficult it would have been
星尘号的科研团队
and how time-consuming
解决彗星材料微粒的捕捉问题
for the Stardust team to locate these microscopic pieces
是如何困难 如何旷日持久
of cometary material inside the aerogel.
当星尘号回到地球
Upon Stardust's return to Earth,
科学家从气凝胶里找到了1万多块
scientists recovered over 10,000 cometary fragments
彗星碎片
from the aerogel.
通过化学分析 发现在微粒里
Chemical analysis revealed that the particles
含有机化合物甘氨酸
contained the organic compound glycine,
这是生命的基础主材之一
a fundamental building block of life
在40多亿年间 一直被保存在冰块里
that had been preserved in ice for over 4 billion years.
彗星里有机化合物的发现
The discovery of organic compounds in comets
说明了有机化合物很容易形成
suggests that organic compounds can form pretty easily.
它不能说明在彗星上有过活着的生命
Now, it doesn't mean that there was ever anything truly alive
但至少说明了生命的基础材料
in those comets, but at least the building blocks of life
曾在彗星上形成过
could have been built in comets.
彗星似乎能保留非常宝贵的
Comets appear to hold invaluable information
关于太阳系起源的信息
about the origin of our solar system
可能还有它本身起源的信息
and perhaps life itself.
但天文学家发现
But astronomers have discovered
这些冰团并非亘古不变
that these icy bodies are not immortal.
现在最先进的卫星拍摄到
Now state-of-the-art satellites have captured images
一群彗星将会踏上
of a select group of comets that will end their life
自杀之旅
in a suicidal death dive.
我们觉得与彗星的同行
While our journey with the comets
就象一个无穷尽的过山车游戏
has felt like an endless cosmic roller coaster ride,
但这些冰团却不会永远绕着太阳飞行
these icy objects will not orbit our Sun forever.
绝大多数还会飞行数千年
Most will make the voyage for several thousand years
直到它们被蒸发掉 只剩下尘埃颗粒
before evaporating into specks of dust.
甚至巨型彗星 比如哈雷彗星
Even massive comets, like Haley,
也只有150 000年的生命
only have 150,000 years left.
这是因为 彗星每一秒都会失去数吨的冰
That's because, every second, a comet loses tons of ice.
彗星会渐渐萎缩或湮灭
Comets gradually wither away or fade away,
因为在临近太阳的每一刻
because every time they pass close to the Sun,
它们都会失去一些冰块
they lose some of their ices.
它们被蒸发了
They evaporate away.
最后 只有很少的冰块留下
Eventually, there's very little ice left,
以至于形成不了彗发和彗尾
and so the comet coma and tail doesn't form.
这时的它象小行星
It just looks like an asteroid.
或者甚至会破碎为许多小物体
Or it may even break apart into a whole bunch of little objects
因为冰的胶合力已不复存在了
because the icy glue is no longer there
或者是潮汐的影响使它发生破裂
or because tidal effects actually break it apart.
但不是所有彗星都会平静地消失在阳光里
But not all comets quietly fade into the sunset.
我们现在正穷追着一群彗星
We're now in hot pursuit of a group of comets
它们被称为"掠日彗星"
called sungrazers
其生命匆匆 分外短暂
that live fast and die young.
当彗星沿着非常狭长的轨道
Inside our spacecraft, we feel the heat
带我们去到离太阳很近
as the comets' extremely elongated orbits
相隔只有数十万英里的地方
bring us very close to the Sun...
飞船里的我们感受到了太阳的炽热
within a few hundred thousand miles.
在这个危险区域里 我们不时看到
As we enter this danger zone,
有一些彗星象日本神风队一样
we see that some of these kamikaze comets
径自冲向太阳
occasionally plunge right into our home star,
上演了一场残忍的告别演出
creating a ferocious spectacle.
掠日彗星的诞生与普通彗星相同
Sungrazer comets start out their life as normal comets.
它们或是居住在奥尔特云
They probably live either in the Oort cloud,
或者本来就是短周期彗星
or they're short-period comets,
但它们的不幸在于 遇上了一个行星
but they've had an unlucky encounter with another planet,
可能是木星
probably Jupiter.
如果它们非常 非常幸运
If they're really, really lucky,
就可以逃脱 从而避免
they might just escape and be able to get away
经过太阳时过于靠近它
with one close passage by the Sun,
如果运气不好 太阳会让它们彻底地灰飞烟灭
but if they're not lucky, they just get swallowed up whole by the Sun.
太阳和太阳风层探测器 简称SOHO
The Solar and Heliospheric Observatory,or SOHO,
是一颗太空卫星
or SOHO, is a space satellite
已经发现了2 000颗正在自杀途中的彗星
that has observed 2,000 comets on suicidal orbits.
最著名的掠日彗星是克鲁兹族彗星
The most famous sungrazers are the Kreutz family,
它们是由一颗巨型彗星
which originated from one giant comet
破裂而成的许多碎片
that broke up into many smaller pieces.
目睹来自外太阳系的彗星
It's a kind of cool thing to think of a comet
一直坠落
that's lived in the outer solar system
在太阳里粉身碎骨
just falling all the way and smashing into the Sun,
感觉真爽 屡看不厌
but they do. We see them all the time.
有些彗星不只是想自杀
And some comets do more than self-destruct.
它们还梦想成为超级杀手
They become the messengers of mass destruction.
巨型彗星撞击地球
It's estimated that a large comet
据估计 大约每4千万年可能发生一次
may have struck Earth roughly every 40 million years,
以至于如今的地球还残留许多明显弹坑
based on the amount of craters still visible on our planet.
彗星也许要对地球史上
A comet may have even been responsible
最著名的灭绝事件负责
for the most famous extinction event of all time.
在白垩-第三纪时期发生的
For the Cretaceous-Tertiary extinction event,
6千5百万年前恐龙灭绝
the one that took out the dinosaurs
其原因至今没有定论
65 million years ago, the jury is still out.
人们认为是一个直径10公里的物体
That was thought to be a 10-kilometer-sized object,
但在地球附近 没有小行星
and there are no asteroids in near-Earth space
可以把地球撞击得如此惨烈
that are that large that could impact the Earth,
却有为数不少的巨型彗星
and there are a number of comets that are that large.
况且那是发生6千5百万年前
And since it occurred 65 million years ago,
而彗星撞击
and you would expect a cometary impact
大约是每4千万年一次
every 40 million years or so,
所以它可能就是彗星
it may well have been a comet.
由于彗星在过去
While comets likely slammed into Earth
有可能无数次撞击过地球
countless times in the past,
所以很难以判定
it's been difficult to determine
一个撞击坑是由彗星还是小行星产生的
if an impact crater was made by a comet or asteroid
毕竟这两种物体很类似
because the two bodies appear to be similar.
我们通过研究化石
When we study the fossil records,
发现了大量的罕见材料
a lot of the material is gone, and just-we simply can't find it,
但彗星与小行星有许多共同的原材料
and it turns out that asteroids and comets have a lot of materials in common,
所以 即使你发现了外星物质
so even if you do find extraterrestrial material,
也难于分清楚
it's really hard to tell
它到底来自于小行星 还是彗星
whether it came from an asteroid or from a comet.
彗星撞击地球
And to complicate matters,
引发灾难的话题
a comet doesn't even have to impact Earth's surface
一直众说纷纭
to ignite a catastrophe.
在1908年 一个火球在西伯利亚
In 1908, a fireball exploded in the atmosphere
通古斯地区的荒野上空爆炸
above the Tunguska wilderness in Siberia.
空中爆炸所产生的温度和能量
The heat and energy from the airburst
象热旋风一样往下推进
propelled downward like a hot tornado.
它横扫丛林
It propagated across the forest,
把方圆800英里森林夷为平地
flattening over 800 square miles of trees.
在一个世纪之后 一些科学家猜想
For over a century, some scientists have wondered
这位不速之客是不是彗星或者小行星
if the cosmic intruder was a comet or an asteroid.
如果是彗星
If it were caused by a comet,
你就会在沉积物中
you would imagine you'd find in the sediment
找到一些不寻常的迹象
some record of unusual things,
比如氦-3和氦-4的比例
like a ratio of helium 3 to helium 4.
这才能够说明它可能是彗星
That could be an indication that it may have been a comet.
或者是
Now, another possibility is if you find
在湖里找到奇异的同位素
some strange isotope buried in a lake somewhere.
但这无异于大海捞针
That's tough. This is not easy.
虽然难以证明
While it's been difficult
彗星是否曾撞击地球
to substantiate cometary impacts on Earth,
但有物理证据表明
physical proof of their colossal power
它们在巨型气态行星上威力强大
exists on the gas giant planets.
对地球来说 这些事件是严重的警告
And these dramatic events warn that far worse collisions
在未来的日子里
loom in the future,
极为糟糕的撞击在步步逼近
with Earth as the potential bull's-eye.
我们已经尾随着彗星
As we have followed the trail of comets through space,
穿越了太阳系里
we have passed through the chilliest
极寒冷和极暖和的地方
and warmest places in our solar system.
我们还调查了这些冰团
We've also investigated whether these icy bodies
是否曾经传递和毁灭生命
have been deliverers and destroyers of life.
而且有新证据表明 许多这样的古老物体
And new observations prove many of these ancient bodies
不会在寒冷的外太阳系
haven't quietly retired to the frigid outer limits
安享晚年
of our solar system.
那里有一些晚期的彗星
We think there are several possible end states for comets.
它们一是可能被扯向太阳
In one case, they can actually get pulled right into the Sun.
二是可能被某一个行星
In other cases, they can actually get scattered
强行赶出去
by one of the planets and kind of get kicked out,
或许回到奥尔特云 永远都见不到
maybe back into the Oort cloud and never seen again.
最后一种可能是 它们撞上某个行星
And finally they can also actually impact a planet.
我们现在飞回到1994年的7月
We now shuttle back to July 1994.
我们去追随
We follow a string of
有着21块碎块的苏梅克-列维彗星
21 comet fragments called Shoemaker-Levy 9
观察它们因重力的影响而坠入
as they're gravitationally pulled toward the gas giant
巨型气态行星－木星
planet Jupiter.
如果我们
If we were riding on
和苏梅克-列维彗星碎块一起飞行
one of the fragments of the comet Shoemaker-Levy 9,
就会看到非常壮观的景象
it would have been truly spectacular
因为随着我们的逼近
because we're heading toward Jupiter,
木星这颗巨星变得巨大无比
and this giant planet is looming ever bigger,
接着啪哒作响
and then-splat!
我们撞上它了
We crash into it.
一团烟幕腾天而起
We throw up a whole bunch of material from the insides.
令人叹为观止
It would be really an amazing journey.
撞击剧烈至极 使得烟幕
The plumes of material coming out of Jupiter
饱含因撞击而产生的过热蒸汽
were superheated gas heated by this collision
以及木星的内部物质
and also excavated from the interior of Jupiter.
苏梅克-列维彗星留下的撞击疤痕
Shoemaker-Levy 9 left impact scars
如同地球般大小
the size of Earth,
如果它撞击地球
driving home the scale of violence
后果将不堪设想
that comets can produce if they slam into our planet.
如果这些碎块的任何一块撞击地球
If any of those fragments had hit the Earth
与木星不同 我们会陷入极度危险
rather than Jupiter, we'd have been in serious trouble,
因为它们都是大块头 而且来势迅猛
because they were large and they were coming in extremely rapidly.
但幸运的是 老大哥木星
But fortunately, big brother Jupiter
代我们接受撞击
took all the hits for us and didn't seem to
而且若无其事
suffer much in the way of damage.
但是 尽管有木星这块行星盾牌
But even with Jupiter acting as a planetary shield,
还是会有漏网之鱼
comets still sneak by the gas giants
突如其来地接近地球
and have close encounters with Earth.
好消息是
The good news is,
在近地空间里 袭击地球的
asteroid impacts are far more likely to occur
更多时候是小行星 因为它们的数量
because asteroids outnumber comets 100 to 1
比彗星多100倍
in near-Earth space.
坏消息是 如果彗星沿着
The bad news is, if we do find a comet
撞击地球的轨道飞行
on an Earth-impacting trajectory,
我们不会有所察觉
we wouldn't realize it
除非它在进入木星轨道时
till it got inside the orbit of Jupiter,
会开始喷发气体和尘埃
when it started throwing off gas and dust.
虽然彗星接近地球不太可能
In the very unlikely event that a comet
但你要考虑它
could get close to the Earth, you would worry about it
因为其平均速度要高于小行星
because they tend to have high average velocities relative to an asteroid,
达到每秒几十英里
as high as tens of miles a second.
也就是说 它们出拳凶猛有力
So in other words, they would pack a bigger punch.
邻近地球的小行星数量众多
While the frequency of near-Earth asteroids
袭击地球的可能性很高
heightens the risk of impacts,
但彗星的速度同样令人不安
the speed of comets is equally troubling.
佛罗里达州波尔得市的观测者
This sobering fact has prompted
罗宾 W.意识到了事情的严重性
viewer Robin W. from Boulder, Colorado, to...
询问宇宙
对人类更有危险的 是小行星还是彗星？
What poses a greater hazard to humans: asteroids or comets?
罗宾 这问题非同小同
Robin, that's an important question.
小行星数不胜数
The asteroids are more numerous,
很多都有可能撞击我们
so there's more of them that could hit us.
但我们能跟踪它们的轨迹
But we can track their trajectories
对即将到来的撞击采取措施
and maybe do something about one that's gonna hit us,
比如让它转向
deflect it for example.
彗星相对较为罕见
The comets are more rare,
但我们难以觉察它们的到来
but we have very little warning when they come in.
而且 它们的速度比小行星快得多
And also, they move much faster than asteroids,
撞击地球的能量更大
so there's more energy impacting Earth.
所以我认为 彗星最危险
So I would say comets are the most hazardous objects.
询问宇宙
NASA很认真地对待彗星的威胁
NASA is taking the threat of comets seriously.
迄今为止 负责跟踪的卫星
So far, tracking satellites
已经辨识到84颗靠近地球的彗星
have tagged 84 near-Earth comets,
其轨道是在地球绕太阳公转路线的
objects with orbits that come within 28 million miles
2千8百万英里范围内
of Earth's path around the Sun.
眼下还没有
There are no periodic comets
喜欢上地球的周期彗星
that currently have Earth's name written on them.
但木星和其它的巨型行星
But Jupiter and the other giant planets
偶尔会扰乱彗星的轨道
occasionally perturb the orbits of comets.
所以未来应该会有一颗周期彗星
So there could be a periodic comet in the future
与地球相撞
that will collide with Earth.
自有史记载以来
Since the beginning of recorded history,
被发现的彗星超过 4 200颗
over 4,200 comets have been observed,
但这只是这些冰团的一小部分
a mere fraction of the total number of these icy bodies.
这意味着数百万的未知彗星
This means billions of unknown comets
还在外层空间潜伏着 等待着
still lie in wait in the outer reaches of space.
某一天 一颗末日彗星会被推出来
One day, a doomsday comet could be nudged out
踏上与地球相撞的旅程
and sent on a collision course with Earth.
假设我们是在宇宙里的高速公路上
If we're on that cosmic highway,
而它开进了我们的车道
and it's getting into our on-ramp,
我们需要提防它
we need to worry about it.
但我们只有非常短的反应时间
And we need to worry about it with very little lead time.
我们别无选择
There is very little we can do,
只能向它们发射巨型原子弹
other than sending a giant bomb toward them
设法让它们转向
and trying to deflect them.
但非常棘手的是
But that's very difficult
我们只有几个月的预警时间
when there's only a few months' warning.
正如彗星让我们的祖先
Just as comets have inspired awe and fear
感到无比的敬畏和害怕
among our ancestors,
它们今天依然不可藐视
they remain a force to reckon with.
通过持续追踪它们的尘埃尾巴
By continuing to track their tails of dust,
我们也许能发现关于我们遥远过去的
we may uncover more clues about these frozen artifacts
更多线索
of our ancient past.
你会觉得它很不寻常
It's pretty remarkable if you think about it.
在数百年前 我们不知道它们是什么
Just a few hundred years ago, we had no idea what they were.
不知道它们的意义
We had no idea what they meant.
但现在我们已经去到了彗星表面
And now we've actually been to the surfaces of comets.
近距离地观察它们 去研究
We've seen up close and personal what they're really like
它们的组成
and what they're made out of.
总之 这些神秘之物对人类
So these mysterious objects have meant a lot to humans
意义非同凡响
throughout our history.
它们曾被视为异兆
They've been agents of change.
它们有时被当作灾星
They've been agents of destruction sometimes.
它们也许曾是造物使者
They've maybe been agents of creation.